Robert Garrett Collection of Ethiopic Magic Scrolls, 1700-1900: Finding Aid C0744.04
Manuscripts Division
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 155, late 19th century; 155; 1 box 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a poor hand (2-3mm). 2 talismanic drawings. The bottom portion of the scroll is missing. 875 x 87mm (Box 4)
  Grid pattern with three faces in the central row of squares and alternate eye-motif and transverse cross designs in the others, placed between borders of further transverse cross and eye-motifs. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Lobed transverse cross with eye-motifs. (In ink with red-brown and yellow color.)
  Owner: Wälättä Te'emarä Dengel (f.)
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 156, early/mid 19th century; 156; 1 box 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a neat hand (4mm). 2 talismanic drawings. Preserved in a leather cylinder case. 960 x 82mm (Box 4)
  Prayer for the protection of the soul invoking the secret names of God, and later employing magic names or asmat. Hymn of salutation to Phanuel, the "Banisher of Demons."
  Cross, the arms with scale-motif infill, set between a pair of lattice-work borders. (In ink with yellow and red-brown color.)
  Seraph, set between a pair of diaper-pattern borders. (In ink with red-brown and yellow color.)
  Owner: Hezqeyas (m.)
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 157, mid 19th century; 157; 1 box Single piece of parchment. 2 cols., written in black with rubrics in an uneven and angular hand (4-5mm), separated by a simple uncolored linear border. No drawings. 600 x 200-255mm (Box 4)
  Sälam [hymn of salutation] to Neburä Ed Wäldä Giyorgis, "The Most High and Beloved of God, the Builder of the Second Jerusalem, Zion." In Ge'ez except for the last 4 lines.
  Owner: None identified.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 158, late 19th century; 158; 1 box 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a moderate hand (3-4mm), framed within a narrow lattice-work border colored blue and red. 3 talismanic drawings and 1 grid chart. There is some rubbing and water damage to the scroll. 1887 x 90mm (Box 4)
  Extensive prayer or sequence of prayers for undoing spells (mäftehé deray).
  Eight-pointed star or cross with central face, the arms each ending in a lobe with an eye motif. The whole set between lattice-work borders. (In ink with faded red, yellow and blue color.)
  Grid chart with infill of magic words or names in each square, alternately written in red and black.
  Cross with checkerboard pattern infill and lobed designs between the arms. (In ink with red, yellow and blue color.)
  Hand-cross design. (In ink with red, blue and yellow color.)
  Owners: Gäbrä Täklä Haymanot (m.) and Wälättä Abiyyä Egzi' (f.)
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 159, 1830-1870; 159; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an indifferent hand (3-4mm). 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 4)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face and eye motifs in each quadrant. (In ink with pale red and yellow color.)
  Another eight-pointed star design with a central face, set between borders with simple chevron decoration. (In ink with pale red and yellow color.)
  A pair of lobed transverse crosses with eye-motif infill. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Hand-cross design. (In ink with pale red and yellow color.)
  Owner: Wälättä Säma'et (f.)
  - Prayer against Zar, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Incorporates the stories of the Gadarene Swine from the Gospel of Matthew, the man possessed by an evil spirit from the Gospel of Mark, and the man healed of possession by an evil spirit by the shores of the Sea of Galilee from the Gospel of Luke. The text also contains the opening of the Gospel of John.
  - Prayer against the Demons of the Air (Yä'ayär Aganent [sic]), mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against "Foul Légéwon That Cuts the Hearts of Men", mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Barya "Of the House", mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Diseases of the Stomach or Liver (Hemamä Käbd), mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Diseases "Of the Air" (Hemamä Ayär), mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 160, 1850-1899; 160; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a neat hand (5mm). 3 drawings. (Box 4)
  Crucifixion. The larger figure of Christ appears on the central cross flanked by the two thieves on smaller crosses; a hand-cross appears between Christ and the right-hand thief. The whole is framed within an oblong linear border with vine-like decoration above and lattice-work decoration below. (In ink with faded red, blue and yellow color.)
  The Virgin Mary and a smaller figure, again framed within an oblong border with lattice-work decoration at the top and bottom. (In ink with red, yellow and blue color.)
  A two-part composition: above, Christ crowned with thorns. Christ appears as a large crowned and robed figure with the stigmata in his hands, whilst above him two smaller figures hammer the thorns into his head. Below, the Resurrection. The large figure of Christ carrying a banner or staff rises from a shrouded corpse, while two smaller figures look on. (In ink with orange-red, blue and yellow color.)
  Owner: Gäbrä Täklä Haymanot (m.)
  - The Text Known as the Bandlet of Righteousness or Lefafä S'edq, Including Five Prayers Entitled the Prayer of the Way to Heaven (S'älot Zämängädä Sämay), circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer of the Agony of Death (S'älot Bä'entä S'a'erä Mot), circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - A Further Prayer Entitled the Prayer of the Way to Heaven, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 161, 1870-1899; 161; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a mediocre hand (), framed within a lattice-work border with yellow and faded red color. 2 talismanic drawings. The bottom portion of the scroll is missing. (Box 4)
  A large guardian spirit figure, the head of which is formed of a two-headed serpent which encircles the prominent eyes; the body with its raised arms is reduced to a a block the lower part of which is decorated with overlapping scale-motifs. (In ink with red, yellow and blue color.)
  Large figure of a guardian angel holding a drawn sword. (In ink with red, blue and yellow color.)
  Owner: Wälättä Arägawi (f.)
  - Prayer for Binding Demons. Account of How Mary Banished Demons With Magic Words. Solomon's Words of Power for Subduing Demons. Text for Banishing Shotälay and Shotälawit by Confession of Faith, late 19th century; 1 item
    Unusually placed above the first drawing and framed within a lattice-work and eye-motif border.
  - Prayer against Rheumatism, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer and Legend of St. Susenyos, late 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 162, 1870-1899; 162; 2 pieces of thin parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics (in bright red European ink) in a mediocre hand (3-4mm), framed within a simple linear border with some yellow color. 2 talismanic drawings. (Box 4)
  Eight-pointed star with central face and four further faces in the spaces between the arms, top, bottom, left and right; arabesques link the remaining arms. (In ink with red ink color.)
  Guardian angel holding a drawn sword. (In ink with some red ink color.)
  Owner: Ehetä Maryam (f.) with the given name Tayyäch.
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage and Shotälay, Aynä Wärq, Aynä S'ela Wägi, Zar, Teyazhir, Barya and Légéwon, and Problems of Conception, late 19th century; 1 item
    Includes the story of the woman with an issue of blood from the Gospel of Mark.
  - Prayer against Diseases of Barya, Légéwon, Aynä S'ela Wägi, Zar, Qurañña, Demons and Devils, late 19th century; 1 item